<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Morning musings</title>
<link>https://khufkens.com/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://khufkens.com/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.55</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The lack of consent</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Erik Mclean on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Too late, I finally picked up “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braiding_Sweetgrass">Braiding Sweetgrass</a>” by Robin Wall Kimmerer. Although the book talks about natural history, the one thing that really stuck was the idea of a gift culture, a culture of gratitude. This culture of gratitude is rooted in asking for consent, from people and the material world alike.</p>
<p>This culture runs counter to how business, politics, life is run throughout most of the Western world. Our Western culture is permeated by the age old adage: “It is easier to ask for forgiveness than to get permission (consent) - anonymous”. In a supreme demonstration of this principle, OpenAI launched their voice assistant Sky using a voice which was <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/05/20/1252495087/openai-pulls-ai-voice-that-was-compared-to-scarlett-johansson-in-the-movie-her">eerily close to that of Scarlett Johansson</a>. They tried to get Johansson’s consent, did not get it, and pushed ahead anyway. Obviously a public outcry followed, Johansson lawyered up and OpenAI had to back track. Mea-culpa, all is forgiven?</p>
<p>Yet, all too often such actions result in a “fait accompli” situation, where a situation can’t be undone after the fact, or legal action is slow and ineffective, or both. Mostly, this is exactly what is desired and not a mistake. OpenAI’s ChatGPT model is for example driven of reams of copyrighted material, for which they did not ask permission, only to force upon us this technology (fait accompli copyright infringements included, with a sue me if you can attitude). This culture, where a particular idea/product/political decision is the end-all be-all, is a culture of contempt and to me seems mostly rooted in a lack of asking for (democratic) consent.</p>
<p>An example close to home resulted in ignoring the environmental impact of PFAS pollution around the Antwerp 3M plant. This contempt of the health of the local population, <a href="https://www.vrt.be/vrtnws/en/2023/05/16/_nuisance-neighbour-3m-order-to-compensate-family/">within the context of new road construction</a>, resulted in a <a href="https://apache.be/2021/08/27/als-chemiebedrijf-3m-vraagt-draait-provincie-antwerpen">political bargain with 3M</a> while sidelining popular concerns and their consent on any (in) action.</p>
<p>More often than not, Western culture doesn’t ask for consent from people or in the indigenous context from all beings around us. It should be acknowledged that there are (environmental) impact studies. But, all too often, these are seen as mere bureaucratic obstacles which can be sidelined by legalese or outright ignoring them to force a “fait accompli” end-game. Our culture is not one of asking for consent, and then only taking half what we desire to safeguard regeneration, as is the indigenous one. To our own detriment, Western culture has lost this consent culture, and the connection with the land, a long time ago in favour of a Machiavellist winner take all philosophy.</p>
<p>“<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apr%C3%A8s_moi,_le_d%C3%A9luge">Après nous, le déluge</a>”, and a belated ‘mea culpa’ for all which was lost.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2024,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {The Lack of Consent},
  date = {2024-05-21},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2024. <span>“The Lack of Consent.”</span> May 21, 2024.
<a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/">https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>culture</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>op-ed</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/contempt-consent-AI-culture/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Good AI, Bad AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Kevin Ku on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Research could greatly benefit from machine learning (these days called AI ). But, as always automation begs the question ‘cui bono’, who benefits. In this context two barriers for equitable AI crystallize. On the one hand the question of fair and well compensated labour, on the other hand the issue of monopolization and concentration of AI power.</p>
<p>In a recent piece in PNAS the advantages of AI in a lab setting are outlined. This editorial is wildly enthousiastic about the potential of AI to increase research outputs, deal with drudgery of lab work and reduce costs by pooling resources.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2406320121">https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2406320121</a></p>
<p>Although some of these talking points are valid, and efficiency gains can be beneficial it is all too clear that the human perspective in this context was lost. These AI lab machines will most likely, but not necessarily, decrease the number of jobs. However, for they sure will create poor quality jobs. Amazon has recently shown that <a href="https://gizmodo.com/amazon-reportedly-ditches-just-walk-out-grocery-stores-1851381116">AI cosplay has been a front for outsourcing cashier jobs to “mechanical turks” abroad</a>.</p>
<p>Having worked in (wet) labs myself, technicians are critical to the functioning of a lab and provide strategic feedback on experimental design. However, technicians are often overlooked - deemed easily replaced and or automated away - and the ultimate target of the PNAS article.</p>
<p>At a most basic level the future of a lab, as described in the article, is one where the lab technician is relegated to the basement to tend to a zoo of buzzing machines, churning jobs to the demand of a ticketing system while having even less social interaction than a line worker in an auto plant. This is a rather bleak future of what a lab could look like. More so, it is disingenuous and hides the fact that this isn’t an AI revolution, it is a way to justify debasing someone’s work conditions using the threat of AI.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As noted in the PNAS article “At Emerald Cloud Lab, researchers and students can order experiments online. A combination of robotic instrumentation and <strong>trained technicians</strong> will perform the experiments as specified.” (emphasis my own)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>People could always be put in a central facility with a ticketing system and a slew of machines to tend to. Until now, that argument wasn’t nearly as appealing if you can’t threaten the lab techs involved with the argument that they should shut up, abandon their unions, or they will be replaced completely by machines - tomorrow. AI as blackmail. During every technological revolution jobs were created, but ultimately many were destroyed as well with people’s livelihoods put on the line - here and now. Many more jobs decreased in quality and compensation.</p>
<p>Many researchers think they will be able to escape this precarity dance, if not gain some edge. I would agree, AI will increase the speed of some tasks significantly and open research avenues. I’ve leveraged some of this in the past myself. However, what many people have lost sight of is that most of these tools are (already) being centralized (in monopolies). Large foundation models, underpinning “cutting edge” research, can only be produced by very large commercial labs. To be of note in such a research environment requires money, connections or both. This further dispels the myth of merit in research, and shows the clear hand of capital while the invisible hand will slap you into oppression.</p>
<p>In short, this cuts short any ability of smaller labs to make sizable contributions. The current AI gold rush will lead to the further stratification of an already hierarchical academic research system of have and have nots. The created models will be “open”, but only the fortunate few will be able to fully exploit them (i.e.&nbsp;reproduce and built upon the theory and data - if provided). This will concentrate research and capital. The future of research will not be determined by how many post-docs you let sleep under their desk, but how much cloud compute you can squeeze from large vendors with your grant.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2024,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Good {AI,} {Bad} {AI}},
  date = {2024-04-28},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2024. <span>“Good AI, Bad AI.”</span> April 28, 2024. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/">https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>op-ed</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/good-AI-bad-AI/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Poor failure modes</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Kelly Sikkema on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I teach people in project (code) management to fail gracefully. When things fail you should have an easy recovery, and a backup plan. Without change, climate change policy will not fail gracefully. The recent shoulder shrugs on reporting of a slowing Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC), an ocean current redistributing heat across the Atlantic with local and global climate importance, only confirm this historical stance.</p>
<p>This means that students have to document what they do, but also trap errors in their reasoning and/or use cases of whomever comes after them. Similarly, I tell students that when managing a project the need to walk through scenarios which might mess up all remaining work, i.e.&nbsp;single points of failure. For anything important, you need to mitigate issues upfront and have possible adaptation options. Generally, you can’t afford single points of failure.</p>
<section id="a-single-point-of-failure" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-single-point-of-failure">A single point of failure</h3>
<p>Climate tipping points are single points of failure. Tipping points impose rapid and irreversible change and excludes graceful failure as the speed at which it occurs excludes adaptation.</p>
<p>A recent article in Science Advances zooms in on the issue of the slowing down or collapse of the AMOC. It solidifies previous statistical work around the weakening of the AMOC, and finds early warning signals in line with previous studies.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adk1189">https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adk1189</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/feb/09/atlantic-ocean-circulation-nearing-devastating-tipping-point-study-finds">https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/feb/09/atlantic-ocean-circulation-nearing-devastating-tipping-point-study-finds</a></p>
<p>This latest study has a number of climate scientists shifting uncomfortably in their chairs. The hope was, given uncertainties in previous studies, that it might all not go too fast. Sadly, this research confirms this previous work, with physical modelling supporting the previous statistical analysis. Currently, there are numbers floating around the scientific community for this shift to start happening potentially as early as mid-century (2050).</p>
<p>The consequences of this tipping point, as outlined in the paper, are profound and would unfold over short decades. It would mean a rapid decline in temperature and precipitation in Europe, and the reversal of the seasonal rains across the Amazon (jeopardizing another potential tipping point). These changes would unfold too quickly for adaptation of say agricultural policy.</p>
<p>Yet, from a policy perspective we collectively seem to look at this and shrug while rapidly progressing towards this tipping point, from a position which already is too close for comfort. Given the stakes of this particular tipping point one would expect more profound actions, and a sense of urgency.</p>
<p>To quote Jeffrey Kargel, senior scientist at the Planetary Science Institute in Arizona, to CNN:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>… a potentially imminent shutdown of the AMOC “will remain somewhat controversial until, one year, we know that it is happening.”</p>
<p>– Jeffrey Kargel</p>
<p><a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2024/02/09/climate/atlantic-circulation-collapse-weather-climate/index.html">https://edition.cnn.com/2024/02/09/climate/atlantic-circulation-collapse-weather-climate/index.html</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>One can only conclude that climate policy, even in the face of overwhelming evidence, seems to have a very poor failure mode.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2024,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Poor Failure Modes},
  date = {2024-02-10},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2024. <span>“Poor Failure Modes.”</span> February 10,
2024. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/">https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>policy</category>
  <category>society</category>
  <category>climate change</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/poor-failure-modes-climate-change/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On the sharing economy</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>from the archive, first published on 2015-02-09</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Elaine Casap on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some things in life are free, yet fewer things remain each day.</p>
<p>Erosion of altruism, acts of kindness and true sharing has in large part been facilitated by the recent buzz around the “sharing” economy. In a sharing economy, or collaborative consumption, owners rent out goods or time they are not using in a peer-to-peer fashion. A common premise is that when goods and services are shared, the value of those goods may increase, for the business, for individuals, and for the community.The sharing economy allows people to offer rides through a service such as Uber and Lyft. Using AirBnB an unused room can be a source of income. While TaskRabbit makes it possible to offer a pair of helping hands while cleaning. More recently there has been as steady increase in services such as education and consultancy through sites such as Udemy and HourlyNerd.</p>
<section id="disruption-and-deregulation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disruption-and-deregulation">Disruption and (de)regulation</h2>
<p>On the surface it seems promising, being hailed as ‘disruptive’ to entrenched businesses such as the taxi service and hotel industry, stirring on innovation. Although the short term advantages for consumers are all too obvious, lower taxi fares and cheaper rooms, the long term impact on society might be less rosy. Here the disruptive nature of these companies goes well beyond just innovating. More often than not these initiatives are successful because they avoid proper regulation protecting both parties as well as legally due taxes. Although AirBnB has been forced to pay tourist taxes in a <a href="http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/working-together-collect-remit-washington-d-c-chicago-illinois/">growing number of cities</a>, the fact that renting out a room stays largely unregulated still provides an unfair advantage compared to local official businesses but also allows abuse.</p>
<p>Countless AirBnB mishaps can be found on the internet; such as the comedian coming home to an orgy, rooms turning into <a href="http://nypost.com/2014/04/14/hookers-using-airbnb-to-use-apartments-for-sex-sessions/">brothels</a> and <a href="http://nypost.com/2014/03/17/airbnb-renter-claims-he-returned-home-to-an-orgy/">houses being trashed</a>. Due to a lack of screening not only are clients a potential treat to a service provider’s property, service providers are also a potential treat to clients. Uber has gotten a bad rep recently by increasing number of sexual <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/06/04/more-bad-news-for-uber-driver-arrested-in-los-angeles-rape-case.html">assault cases by drivers</a> and <a href="http://abc7news.com/archive/9377925/">accidents</a>. The freedom and lack of regulations which makes these services competitive can also turn into a hazard for both the service provider as well as their clients.</p>
</section>
<section id="social-upheaval" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="social-upheaval">Social upheaval</h2>
<p>More damaging than the direct dangers are the indirect consequences of the sharing economy. Within a sharing economy, every item in your household or every idle minute turns into an opportunity cost. Things sitting on a shelf, or time not spend working equals a loss of additional income. All of the sudden, where people used to share equipment and time, now they find or offer these ‘services’ through an app, paying or providing for what was otherwise a free community service. As the demand for these ‘sharing’ services is rising it leaves me with one question: Where did we lose our personal connection to our next door neighbours to the point where we need to use the internet to borrow a hedge trimmer?</p>
<p>Even if people used to pay for certain services, for example baby sitting, the price of these services was governed by local economics. Services were offered through word of mouth and prices were set relative to the local market. Yet, the networked nature of the sharing economy opens up the whole market to service providers far outside local communities. This creates a race to the bottom in hourly wages due to an ever expanding supply of service providers. Combined with a still rotten economy, people will cut corners everywhere cutting into hourly wages, further <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/pascalemmanuelgobry/2014/04/09/the-distributive-implications-of-the-sharing-economy/">weakening the financial position of the middle class and working poor</a>.</p>
<p>The promise of upward social and economic mobility through the sharing economy is therefore broken from the onset. Even worse, it has the potential to cannibalize current full time jobs. Landing people with a ‘job’ <a href="http://www.newrepublic.com/article/120378/wonolo-temp-worker-app-shows-scary-future-sharing-economy">without social protection</a>, benefits or fixed hours and a steady income.</p>
</section>
<section id="true-sharing-and-social-economic-empowerment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="true-sharing-and-social-economic-empowerment">True sharing and social-economic empowerment</h2>
<p>As the sharing economy is making it easy to find ‘shared’ goods and services it makes us ever more distant from the same goods and services we would have otherwise enjoy for free, at the cost of true sharing. The sentiment might be changing with more and more people acknowledging the social and economic implications of the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2015/01/15/the-sentiment-on-sharing-is-shifting/">‘sharing economy’</a> with the potential to move from commodity to commons.</p>
<p>Moving commodity to commons has been happening for a long time. However, it wasn’t covered with the verbal fluff or bad habits of ‘the sharing economy’. Before Udemy made <a href="https://chronicle.com/article/Here-Comes-Professor-Everybody/151445">everyone a professor</a> there was the major push for towards Massive Open Online Courses (MOOC), mainly provided by major universities. Similarly, plenty of online tutorials can be found on YouTube, made by enthousiast and professionals. For example, countless people dedicate their free time mapping the planet. Often beating Google in accuracy and update frequency during <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org/updates/2013-11-17_r%C3%A9ponse_dopenstreetmap_au_typhon_haiyan_yolanda">disaster relief</a>. These services, as well as plenty others provided by the open source software community allow people to use, software, data and knowledge free of charge. These true sharing initiatives are not limited to the software world be extend into the physical world by services such as <a href="https://www.peerby.com/">Peerby</a> which facilitates the borrowing of things in your neighbourhood (without charging for it) or <a href="http://hackerspaces.org/wiki/">Hacker spaces</a> which provide free or low cost access to (specialized) tools.</p>
<p>As always, technology can be used for good as well as for bad. While venture capital clearly benefits from the sharing economy, with Uber being valued at <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2014/12/16/an-uber-valuation-comes-with-uber-problems/">$40 billion</a>, the final gains for the service providers might erode over time. At the same time, these commercial services eat into the social fabric that makes people borrow stuff from neighbours without a fee. I hope with time a <strong>true</strong> sharing economy will prevail.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2024,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {On the Sharing Economy},
  date = {2024-01-28},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2024. <span>“On the Sharing Economy.”</span> January 28,
2024. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/">https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>policy</category>
  <category>society</category>
  <category>archive</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/from-the-archive-the-sharing-economy/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creative and intellectual poverty</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Academia suffers from cognitive and intellectual poverty due to a persistent (time) scarcity mindset (imposed by poor incentives). It is well documented that financially poor people <a href="https://www.apa.org/monitor/2014/02/scarcity">suffer from a scarcity mindset</a>, which erodes core cognitive functions. This scarcity mindsets clouds decisions, prioritizing small short-term gains over long-term larger profits by affecting planning ability.</p>
<p>A recent studies highlighted the decline in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04577-5">disruptive science</a> (Kozlov, Nature 2023) and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03974-8">record number of paper retractions</a> (Van Noorden, Nature 2023). I would argue that this, in part, is driven by a scarcity mindset leading to creative and intellectual poverty.</p>
<p>Scientists have, over time, been forced from a position of relative creative freedom into one which often focuses on chasing (more) funding. Although the true role of scientists is creative discovery and to train a new generation of scientists, this role has taken a back seat. The scarcity mindset in chasing funding has polluted and crowded out creativity and mentorship for all but the lucky few, who have some financial stability or idealistic willingness.</p>
<p>By consequence, mentoring has little priority outside the performative duties, happily offloaded to adjunct “teaching” professors or post-docs where possible. Phds and post-docs are left to <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/how-get-what-you-need-your-phd-or-postdoc-supervisor">fend for themselves</a> in many cases, being left with <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/scientists-aren-t-trained-mentor-s-problem">little or no true guidance</a>. In this context, students, Phds and post-docs are increasingly seen as cheap labour, not an opportunity to teach the next generation of scientists.</p>
<p>Ultimately, this scarcity mindset not only affects students, Phds and post-docs poorly (as extensively documented) it is also is detrimental to science in general. As Kozlov has shown, disruptive science has decreased, while year-over-year the working conditions of Phds and post-docs <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-00332-6">are described as barely scraping by</a>. More so, it is an incentive to let things slide, and opening the door to poor research if not outright <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/when-postdoc-in-my-lab-committed-fraud-i-had-to-face-my-culpability">fraud</a> to get ahead.</p>
<p>The net societal gain of the academic scarcity mindset is therefore slim. The personal cost, for the next generation of scientists, lacking mentorship, all the more dire. As with true poverty, a scarcity mindset is generational, where people who get out of poverty will suffer from this mindset for many years after, perpetuate all its ills and slow down the needed personal changes.</p>
<section id="escaping-the-scarcity-trap" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="escaping-the-scarcity-trap">Escaping the scarcity trap</h3>
<section id="acknowledge-mentorship" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledge-mentorship">Acknowledge mentorship</h4>
<p>Mentorship is theoretically central to the task of academic faculty. Acknowledge this role, and avoid window dressing with numbers. Show up and stand up for students, and move the discussion from results to the process on how to work and manage efficiently, and larger / long term goals which do not necessarily include components which are academically commensurable.</p>
</section>
<section id="build-with-and-for-people-relentlessly" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="build-with-and-for-people-relentlessly">Build with and for people, relentlessly</h4>
<p>Funding and investing in mentorship are not mutually exclusive, but have a higher upfront cost (in time). However, building things with highly trained people is also more efficient. Consider the long term pay-off on investing in people, and working with them.</p>
</section>
<section id="manage-down-then-up." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="manage-down-then-up.">Manage down, then up.</h4>
<p>Most professors manage up, i.e.&nbsp;they try to coerce favours/collaborations with their peers or administrators higher up. Although this is often required, the needs of a lab are larger than the personal project needs of a professor. Without managing down and acknowledging the foundation of a research group, i.e.&nbsp;taking stock and aligning values with anyone you work with, it will be hard to address the true needs of a lab. If people need to <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/how-get-what-you-need-your-phd-or-postdoc-supervisor">actively manage up to get what they need from a supervisor</a> there is something amiss. Practice active listening and be pro-active. Tap into your experience to anticipate the (practical and other) needs of people, adjust in deliberation.</p>
</section>
<section id="understand-lab-cultures" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understand-lab-cultures">Understand lab culture(s)</h4>
<p>Lab culture changes over time and with backgrounds, diversity, generations, technologies, overall societal cultural expectations and across institutions. Acknowledge this fact and try to understand these varying dynamics. Being stuck in your own generation will limit the ways in which you can communicate with those who you mentor. Try to bridge cultural divides actively.</p>
</section>
<section id="be-generous-and-invert-implicit-power-dynamics" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="be-generous-and-invert-implicit-power-dynamics">Be generous, and invert implicit power dynamics</h4>
<p>Even tenure track professors are in a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01425-4">position of power</a> relative to those on fixed-term contracts (phds / post-docs). Acknowledge this privilege by actively lifting people up and creating opportunities for them and with them. Lobby on behalf of students even if this does not directly benefit you.</p>
</section>
<section id="there-is-no-such-thing-as-being-scooped" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="there-is-no-such-thing-as-being-scooped">There is no such thing as being scooped</h4>
<p>Acknowledge that you are part of a scientific dialogue in which certain ideas circulate. Most scientists are not singular geniuses, their work reflects the themes and topics of the societies in which they move. The notion of being scoped, and teaching students to worry about this, only perpetuates a scarcity mindset and intellectual anemia.</p>


</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2024,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Creative and Intellectual Poverty},
  date = {2024-01-18},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2024. <span>“Creative and Intellectual Poverty.”</span>
January 18, 2024. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/">https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>management</category>
  <category>op-ed</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/creative-poverty-scarcity-mindset-academia/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The dying light and the impossibly bright</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Robson Hatsukami Morgan on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Terrestrial astronomy, and the cultural heritage which is our night sky, is being threatened by new sources of light pollution. These new sources of light pollution stem from developing technologies and are harder to mitigate, due to physics and the lack of accountability.</p>
<p>Growing up in Flanders, among the most light polluted areas in the world and the poorest place to attempt to watch the night sky from, I’m keenly aware that light pollution has always plagued visible astronomy observations in more densely populated areas. However, due to the mercury lamps and their narrow spectrum, fixes were available for visible astronomy.</p>
<p>The trend to replace mercury street lights with the more <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/light-pollution-energy-LED-bulbs-spd">energy efficient LED lamps has turned the tables on this fix, and has made light polllution worse</a>. The spectrum of these lights is broader, and therefore harder to filter out. The use of proper lamp fixtures, reducing the use of lights on roads after peak rush hours is more important than ever. For these earth-bound light pollution problems policy and engineering solutions can easily be found. Yet, a new breed of light pollution is far harder to fix, namely space bound / satellite based light pollution.</p>
<p>In recent years, large constellations of satellites have been launched in support of satellite based internet providers such as SpaceX’s Starlink. Starlink alone doubled the orbiting satellites as of writing, where this does not even represents the full constellation! Many more will follow for a similar project the Amazon’s Kuiper project. These platforms, and other private satellites, reflect the Sun’s light and brighten the night sky’s background ever so slightly.</p>
<p>Where for the public the effect might be aesthetic, for astronomers, when zooming in on a small fraction of the sky, these reflections will show up as intrusive streaks across astronomical images acquired for research. In an <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03610-5">opinion piece in Nature</a>, Dr.&nbsp;Sam Lawler describes the full impact of this satellite based light pollution on terrestrial astronomy observations. The take home is that there is little accountability on these matters.</p>
<section id="no-accountability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="no-accountability">No accountability</h2>
<p>Currently, at least two billionaires consider space their private playground, with only partially considering pleas on addressing these light pollution (and other environmental) issues. <a href="https://www.space.com/satellite-megaconstellations-astronomy-dark-skies">Changes are considered where technology allows it</a>, but by and large they force a brighter sky on everyone, hampering research but also space security efforts in monitoring near-earth objects. This untouchable position on how to use space is distressing, but not different from the indifference to public resources of these private companies. In an aside, on the social network Mastodon she also documented the full impact of the legal aspects of this problem. Not only was the article tone policed by the lawyers of Nature, in fear of lawsuits, it was also tacitly acknowledged by the editor that terrestrial based astronomy is mostly on the way out.</p>
<iframe src="https://mastodon.social/@sundogplanets/111596415770041004/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">
</iframe>
<script src="https://mastodon.social/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<p>In this context space based astronomy can not replace terrestrial observations due to the limited capacity of space-borne platforms. More so, depending on the orbit these space telescopes might not be free of the same interference either if flying lower than the offending satellite constellations. It is clear that even outer space and orbital trajectories can become congested, if not dangerously so (e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kessler_syndrome">the Kessler syndrome</a>). Let’s hope that these platforms will show due diligence in cleaning up their act, as well as properly de-orbiting their satellites after use and decreasing their surface brightness dramatically to save our night sky. Little time is left to show these intentions, if not regulation should guarantee all these aspects.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {The Dying Light and the Impossibly Bright},
  date = {2023-12-18},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“The Dying Light and the Impossibly
Bright.”</span> December 18, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/">https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>astronomy</category>
  <category>environment</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/the-dying-light-the-death-of-terrestrial-astronomy/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>End of semester lessons</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by 2y.kang on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The end of the semester is near and code assignments are due. From what I see I can only be proud of the whole class group, with generally well structured projects and clean code.</p>
<p>We live in a world of search and ChatGPT, which make the task of <a href="https://www.theverge.com/22684730/students-file-folder-directory-structure-education-gen-z">teaching data science</a> at times difficult. There is the obvious proliferation of the poor code snippets, but at the heart of it all this sits the ability to easily search unstructured data.</p>
<p>All students have known a world without effective digital search, with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google">Google launching in ~1998</a>. Search dominates everything from laptop menus and smartphones alike. Incentives to sort or structure data are far and few between in their digital world. Yet, in absence of effective search unstructured data is the curse of anyone who needs to curate it - or when collaborating in a team setting. The assumption that effective search will always be available is also a flawed one.</p>
<p>Current advances in LLM now have the ability to expand search past mere indexing into the domain of context aware classification and prompt-based interrogation of digital documents. For example <a href="https://www.bing.com/search?q=Bing+AI&amp;showconv=1&amp;FORM=hpcodx">Bing co-pilot</a> now offers Retrieval-Augmented Generation abilities for free in their search (where search queries “read” webpages and other documents). However, searching through increasing amounts of unstructured data in need of contextualization is predicated on vast amounts of computational power, and does not provide a solution for sharing these searched collections with others.</p>
<p>I’ve always taken the position that small upfront investments in decreasing the cognitive load can vastly improve the ability to search/order data yourself. This is reflected in my data science approaches, providing <a href="https://github.com/bluegreen-labs#teaching-workflows-books">templates</a> for writing software, managing data and organizing research. These techniques are far from new, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">as any librarian will tell you</a>. Libraries used to operate on principles of indexed systems. Everything needs its place and an index structure to be easily searched, without search algorithms.</p>
<p>This semester the students managed to expand their skills both in data science coding, but most importantly in my opinion, in managing their projects cleanly in order to more easily collaborate with others (and their future selves). I think the approach suggested was a gentle introduction on why structure matters, without going full Marie Kondo. I hope these skills serve them well.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {End of Semester Lessons},
  date = {2023-12-16},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“End of Semester Lessons.”</span> December
16, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/">https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/end-of-semester-and-reflections-on-data-management/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brittle code</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Paul Melki on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>From the archive</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Brittle code is code which is hard to maintain and or change. Large projects with brittle code accrue a technological / code debt. Depending on the size of the debt this debt will never be fully repaid, and if it escalates will grind a project to a halt.</p>
<p>Brittle code and code debt is most commonly gathered over time due to a focus on features rather than a focus on maintainability and stability. An initial focus on features is common in growth phases, but consolidation and maintainability should be implemented before widespread use (commercially or privately in a lab setting). These are some tips to avoid brittle code.</p>
<section id="avoiding-brittle-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoiding-brittle-code">Avoiding brittle code</h2>
<p>Brittle code is hard to maintain code. A number of factors affect the maintainability of codebases.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>dependencies</strong></p>
<p>The more dependencies code has the more likely it will break. This situation is critically illustrated by the cartoon below. By extension, never build code on immature external codebases. Maturing code is prone to ad-hoc changes, depreciation of features etc. Keep track of your dependencies!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>size vs.&nbsp;functionality</strong></p>
<p>The larger a codebase the harder it is to maintain, the larger the code debt it carries. Keep projects as large as the basic functionality requires. Extra functionality should reside in a new codebase. Large projects can be split up, but again this comes at a large code debt. It is best to not let a codebase grow beyond its basic use.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>documentation</strong></p>
<p>Document code while you write it, this includes annotations but also formal documentation for users. Putting off writing the documentation and its framework until last will increase your code debt. For formal releases and well documented code consider that up to 50% of your time will be dedicated to documenting user and developer documentation.</p>
<p>Yes, this seems tedious and not necessary at the time, and it isn’t as sexy as implementing that new feature. BUT, if you return to old code and can’t figure out what is going on by reading along you will gather more code debt than it would have cost you to document things up front.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>unit tests</strong></p>
<p>Together with documentation unit tests should be written. This validates the functioning of the code, and ensures that any pull requests submitted works as intended. Failing to do so will increase the code debt of a project, if not that of a colleagues by forwarding issues downstream.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>branches should be short lived</strong></p>
<p>Branches should be short lived and have one particular focus. Stale branches should be deleted. Side development is probably best done in a forked version independent of the main project. Again, long lived branches will gather many functions. These new functions if out of sync with the main branch will create conflicts with other ongoing development. This will generated failed unit tests, and a general brittle state of the codebase. Branch, fix, merge. If a branch is older than two weeks it should probably been a fork (i.e.&nbsp;experimental features - or formal research project, or the assigned taskset is too large - split it up).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>code for the reader</strong></p>
<p>Code for the reader of the code. Compiled code (packages) ignores comments. There is no need to be clever and “short”. Comment what you do in front of chunks (not in chunks as this will overrun line length constraints and give all kinds of compilation issues). Avoid one-liners (nested / piped functions), in this regard the R {tidyverse} and its piped setup can quickly become painful in terms of readability, as it violates this rule. Use the R {tidyverse} sparingly with short piped sections, as it is hard to read / debug with longer constructs.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>personal &amp; team responsibility</strong></p>
<p>As a team you decide to keep code debt low. You don’t have the right to break a code base with the expectation that someone else on the team will fix it (see unit tests above).</p></li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/dependency.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Brittle Code},
  date = {2023-12-13},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Brittle Code.”</span> December 13, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/">https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>management</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <category>archive</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/on-brittle-code-code-debt-and-how-to-avoid-it/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Burn the candle at both ends</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Paul Melki on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Academic researchers are being squeezed from both ends by publishers. This is by design.</p>
<p>Not so long ago Cory Doctorow pitched the word “enshitification” for the state of the internet, and in particular the rise and ultimate decline of (tech) platforms. Per Doctorow, “platforms are firms which mediate between end users and business customers”. In the scorching video at DEFCON31 Doctorow picks apart the decline of these entities, or why they will fold.</p>
<center>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rimtaSgGz_4?si=_GDnlEOprv8fjhyJ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
</center>
<p>Where Uber connects drivers with riders and Amazon connects buyers with sellers. Where first a platform is good to its users, which will then draw business customers. Finally, when both are locked-in, for a lack of alternatives and entrenched patterns, the platform will bring down the hammer on both (extracting all value from both customers and business alike). But, although both users and businesses using the platforms will be robbed they mostly represent separate entities (e.g.&nbsp;drivers and riders of an Uber taxi).</p>
<section id="academic-publishing-as-a-platform" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="academic-publishing-as-a-platform">Academic publishing as a platform</h3>
<p>Now, in the <a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2023/10/30/quantifying-consolidation-in-the-scholarly-journals-market/">effective oligopoly market</a> of academic publishing platforms this is driven to a peak as users and business customers are the same people, only separated by time in their research workflow. Researchers read, “consume”, academic literature, where at the end of their research workflow they are in the business of “producing” new academic literature. The academic publishing platform only mediates between the same group of people separated by time - squeezing them at both ends. This process can only be described as a highly lucrative scam.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Overall, the market has significantly consolidated since 2000 — when the top 5 publishers held 39% of the market of articles to 2022 where they control 61% of it. Looking at larger sets of publishers makes the consolidation even more extreme, as the top 10 largest publishers went from 47% of the market in 2000 to 75% in 2023, and the top 20 largest publishers from 54% to controlling 83% of the corpus. - <a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2023/10/30/quantifying-consolidation-in-the-scholarly-journals-market/">The Scholary Kitchen</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The drive for ever higher returns, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/495426a">reaching up to 30% (with some estimates even higher)</a> and exceeding most tech platforms, puts an extreme burden on researchers and funding agencies. Where the proposed shift towards open access should have resolved some of the woes of accessibility in research, it only has boosted the further enshitification of academic publishing. Publishers actively double dip with mixed “open access” articles in otherwise closed access journals. This requires libraries or individual researches to still pay for journal subscriptions, with only those articles made open by the wealthy.</p>
<p>Increasingly, those same users and business customers are squeezed in other places of the value chain as well. Review times get shorter, paper mills and vacuous “special issues” and the active manipulation of researchers due to social media and other tokens (e.g.&nbsp;AltMetrics and Publons) make research and publishing harder. At the same time, additional value is extracted from the IP signed away and the consolidation of most of the academic workflow in other domains (citation management, data brokerage etc).</p>
</section>
<section id="a-way-out-of-enshitification" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-way-out-of-enshitification">A way out of enshitification</h3>
<p>One has to question, when will this system break? Currently what gets published <a href="https://fediscience.org/@MarkHanson/111147239095599059">outpaces the admission of new PhDs</a>. One can argue that the vast amounts of research published today is either fake or only there to boost someone’s h-index, not the creative enterprise which is science. Sadly, most efforts to address this <a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/science-is-a-strong-link-problem">strong-link problem</a> are on the weak and wrong end of the problem. Listing all predatory journals doesn’t make the good (society) journals stand out more.</p>
<p>A true measure of excellence would require a contextual analysis of scientific research, not only counting citations. Where the creation of Large Language Models might further pollute academic publishing the underlying Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods could offer solutions to provide contextual analysis. But here metrics might soon become the target once more, rather than a means of fair assessment.</p>
<p>The low tech option would be for researchers to step back and demonstrate <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03063-w">academic humility</a>. We need to return to slow, i.e.&nbsp;deliberate and creative scientific research, by abandoning the <a href="https://totalinternalreflectionblog.com/2023/10/29/a-riposte-to-the-red-queens/">Red Queen logic</a> of a publishing treadmill leading nowhere. Excellence should not merely be measured by popularity, but by the quality of the work delivered, the dialogue it opened up, the service it provided to the scientific community or the public, and the long term value of it.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Burn the Candle at Both Ends},
  date = {2023-12-12},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Burn the Candle at Both Ends.”</span>
December 12, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/">https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>publishing</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/enshitification-of-academic-publishing/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lost inner voices</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The Simpsons, Old Man and the Key</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Over the past years I’ve seen a steady decline in the problem solving ability of students. I fear large language models (LLMs), such as ChatGPT, might not do them a favour.</p>
<p>Now, this might sound like an opinion of an “old man yells at cloud”. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2010/06/02/127370598/the-shallows-this-is-your-brain-online">Google (search)</a> and calculators were also once proposed to cause brain rot. But this cuts even deeper.</p>
<p>Most people have some form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intrapersonal_communication">intrapersonal communication</a> or inner-dialogue(s). Forms of self-talk underpin a lot of higher decision making such as self-control, self-direction but also problem solving skills. This self-talk can be positive, or negative, despite it being potentially valuable and insightful as written down by the cult classic “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance">Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</a>” by Robert M. Pirsig. However, it remains largely a personal inner dialogue.</p>
<p>But, not anymore I would argue. A surprisingly large group of people have long and <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/10/people-are-speaking-with-chatgpt-for-hours-bringing-2013s-her-closer-to-reality/">winding conversations with LLMs</a> or have <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/technology/4218666-ai-girlfriends-are-ruining-an-entire-generation-of-men/">AI girlfriends</a>. One can see the sadness that ensues if these LLMs start replacing friendly phone calls, because LLMs are more convenient to talk to as always available and uniquely tuned to your character. But what about our inner-dialogues?</p>
<section id="outsourcing-your-inner-dialogue" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outsourcing-your-inner-dialogue">outsourcing your inner-dialogue</h3>
<p>I think that at least some of us might be in danger of replacing their inner-dialogue with commercial for profit chat bots. These chat bots could make their internal conversation external. Surfacing your self-talk was previously the domain of psychologists or psychiatrists, this is now done under little supervision <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/pkadgm/man-dies-by-suicide-after-talking-with-ai-chatbot-widow-says">at times with deadly consequences</a>.</p>
<p>Even without dramatic consequences, erosion of internal self-critical thought seems innocent but isn’t. Students, well everybody really, need critical problem solving skills. These problem solving skills are eroding fast, on a very basic level running deeper than Google search or calculators, while being supercharged for others.</p>
<p>For those who consciously use these LLMs, being careful on how to deploy them, might actually increase their self-critical skills as it gives them that additional external perspective previously conjured by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber duck debugging</a>, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socratic_method">Socratic (dialectic) method</a> to problem solving. Much of this technology will further entrench social inequity, between those who unconsciously see their inner-voices replaced by commercial entities (for now without ads), and those that know how to game/use the system and mostly pay for quick access, privacy and an ad-free experience.</p>
<p>I fear teaching critical problem solving skills will become more and more challenging in the years to come.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Lost Inner Voices},
  date = {2023-11-05},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Lost Inner Voices.”</span> November 5, 2023.
<a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/">https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/lost-inner-voices-llm-impact-problem-solving-chatgpt-ml-teaching/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On swifts and open science</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Robert Booth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The past week some recent work on swift behaviour got published in <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2023.0957">The Proceedings of the Royal Society B</a>. In this research I, together with a splendid team, discuss the influence of moonlight on flight behaviour and foraging tactics during the non-breeding season (across Africa) of three European swift species. This works follows on previous work <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/oik.08594">in Oikos</a> along the same research lines and by the same team, but led by Lyndon Kearsley, discussing the influence of atmospheric convergence zones on flight behaviour. Combined, these two studies provide an insight into how swifts optimize their behaviour to their flight environment, let it be wind and/or light.</p>
<p>This ornithology research grew out of the passion of Lyndon Kearsley who, as a long-term amateur ornithologist (50+ years), contributes to academic research on a regular basis but rarely as research lead. During the COVID pandemic he shared some of this passion with me, from which grew the plan to publish some of the insights which came from these discussions and subsequent conversations with other collaborators.</p>
<p>Publishing science from the perspective of a small independent lab is certainly not open, as in easily accessible to all, even if ideas are good, the execution of the analysis spot-on, and the data and code openly available. I’m happy with the progress this team makes, but our largely unaffiliated status does not make our work easier. I think the scientific community, despite “broader impacts”, needs to acknowledge and consider outside contributions more seriously. Many fields still struggle with issues surrounding data ownership, proper attribution (of amateurs and citizen scientists), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neo-colonial_science">neo-colonialism</a> and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41561-022-01010-4">helicopter science</a> and a publishing system which is increasingly financially out of reach for smaller labs.</p>
<p>Academic research can be decidedly competitive - chasing a vacuous <a href="https://totalinternalreflectionblog.com/2023/10/29/a-riposte-to-the-red-queens/">Red Queen status quo</a>. But, to end in a positive note, in these swift studies we took an explicit community based approach. BlueGreen Labs, through myself and Lyndon, tries to facilitate slower and open science by building knowledge, software, hardware, and a community surrounding all these aspects. We consciously stepped away from the Red Queen rat race of academic publishing, where we try to partner with diverse collaborators (co-authors) on a basis of a shared passion, expertise and trust.</p>
<p>I think our work reflects the fact that one does not necessarily need a large budget to do impactful and fun science, for all involved. Research needs (interdisciplinary) community, foundation frameworks (among others in good software and hardware stacks and support/teaching), and open and honest communication with less careerism and one-upmanship. To end with a platitude: “If you want to go fast, go alone, if you want to go far, go together”.</p>
<hr>
<section id="references" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h3>
<p>Hufkens, K. et al.&nbsp;(2023), Evaluating the effects of moonlight on the vertical flight profiles of three western palaearctic swifts. Royal Society. doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2023.0957">https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2023.0957</a>.</p>
<p>Kearsley, L. et al.&nbsp;(2022), The aeroecology of atmospheric convergence zones: the case of pallid swifts. Oikos, 2022: e08594. doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.08594">https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.08594</a></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {On Swifts and Open Science},
  date = {2023-11-04},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“On Swifts and Open Science.”</span> November
4, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/">https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>ornithology</category>
  <category>op-ed</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/swift-research-open-science/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Torch/Keras in R</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by British Library on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Recently, I more formally picked up machine learning again - in a more day-to-day fashion rather than one-off projects. Specifically, I’m trying to use R within the context of deep learning. Given that the dominant ecosystem for machine learning mostly remains python this might come as a surprise.</p>
<p>Thing is, I don’t like pivoting in and out of environments. In particular, data wrangling is much easier in R than in python. Given that a good amount of machine learning is dealing with cleaning data and data wrangling it often seems a better fit to use R rather than python (with the exception being image processing).</p>
<p>Anyway, I tried such a deep dive a couple of years ago with the excellent book “<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/deep-learning-with-r-second-edition">Deep Learning with R</a>” by <a href="https://fchollet.com/">Francois Cholet</a>. Sadly, at the time, the R ecosystem of Keras felt very brittle and incomplete. But, revisiting Keras, and Torch, again after a couple of years was a breath of fresh air. The R APIs feel more feature complete and in line with the python one.</p>
<p>The last couple of days I’ve really enjoyed the combination of <a href="https://torch.mlverse.org/">{torch}</a> and {luz} to model ecosystem flux data and phenology. Some key resources have been the Posit.io (rstudio) machine learning blog - which reblogs some of the work in the “<a href="https://skeydan.github.io/Deep-Learning-and-Scientific-Computing-with-R-torch/">Deep Learning and Scientific Computing with R torch</a>” by <a href="https://divergences.xyz/">Sigrid Keydana</a>. Given that the first book by Francois Cholet was brilliant, I assume the second version is better with the increasing ability of TensorFlow and the Keras APIs. Pick up either of these books to get a good handle on machine learning in R. Depending on if and where I find time, I might blog about some tips and tricks.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Torch/Keras in {R}},
  date = {2023-10-30},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Torch/Keras in R.”</span> October 30, 2023.
<a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/">https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/machine-learning-torch-R-luz/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to draw an owl</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<p>Much of project planning resolves around taking an idea, i.e.&nbsp;the badly drawn concept, to a fully detailed drawing (of an owl). However, both images at the beginning only live in your head. The initial idea, and the ideal outcome are separated by what is truly feasible. Most projects fail when they do not account for the practical difference between what it takes to manifest the idea and realize the ideal solution.</p>
<section id="the-process-often-matters-most" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-process-often-matters-most">The process (often) matters most</h2>
<p>Given that no project is free of setbacks of all sorts, it is key to realize that most of the project will be spent not focusing on the final details of the ideal image. Most time will be spent on figuring out ways how to even start drawing (the damn owl). A failure to account for the process and a singular focus on the ideal will run any project into the ground, from a resource or human perspective (causing undue stress).</p>
<p>[Important note: in some projects there is no room for outright failure, but even high risk projects get revisions!]</p>
</section>
<section id="keep-track-of-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="keep-track-of-projects">Keep track of projects</h2>
<p>Given that the project process is more important than the outcome it is key to keep track of progress, more precisely:</p>
<ul>
<li>why you took certain decisions?</li>
<li>what went wrong, and how you resolved it (so others don’t have to repeat this mistake)?</li>
<li>track the physical constraints of an implementation (for Machine Learning this could be GPUs used)?</li>
<li>track limits on scalability (are processes easily parallelizable)?</li>
<li>documentation, documentation, more documentation…</li>
</ul>
<p>Document all these things extensively and show where value was added despite setbacks.</p>
</section>
<section id="failing-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="failing-forward">Failing forward</h2>
<p>Nobody likes to bring bad news, but if your project does not manage to draw (the owl) results finding added value in other aspects of a project is key. This does not only cover lessons learned (as listed above), but also covers proposing ways out of the impasse more generally. You can fail forward by pointing out why things didn’t work out the way it should have happened, but more so, how these issues can be resolved and avoided (and at what cost) in the future.</p>
<p>Where possible generate added value by providing small tangible products during the project. To continue the owl analogy, you might not be able to draw the fully detailed owl, but you might have put together a method to draw a very nice cartoon owl. This, on its own, has a certain value. Discarding this result because it did not meet the ideal would be foolish.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {How to Draw an Owl},
  date = {2023-10-28},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“How to Draw an Owl.”</span> October 28,
2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/">https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>management</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/how-to-draw-an-owl-advice-from-a-meme/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building bridges</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Modestas Urbonas on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This is a quick post of some advice I gave about career development to an early career scientist. Take from it what you want.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Try to build bridges between where you are and where you want to go (this can include people, places, topics, techniques).</p></li>
<li><p>Touching on building, try to build (multiple) things (lines of research, data, code) which outlast singular projects or span several. This is why I’m relentless on using templates and formalizing code. This allows you to recycle old projects in a new context fast, so you can pivot into a new project quicker.</p></li>
<li><p>Diversify your portfolio, don’t get painted into a corner. By definition ecology is interdisciplinary and chances are that you will have to do fieldwork / lab work at some point. Getting experience before you need to supervise people doing so (without any true experience) is key. Use early career years to make mistakes which in a management setting would be unforgivable (as affecting other people’s career - even more than your own).</p></li>
<li><p>Build bridges for other people! The bigger your responsibility (older you are) the more you have the ability to pay it forward (give people opportunities). You shouldn’t cannibalize your own work, but sometimes it is as easy as sending a simple email in support (or letting someone tag along or contribute). Do so!</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Build bridges between people, build frameworks (foundations) to work from / upon, build diversity in your skills / interests / people and if possible encourage, and support, others to do the same.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Building Bridges},
  date = {2023-10-10},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Building Bridges.”</span> October 10, 2023.
<a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/">https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>management</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/building-bridges-science-management/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fresh start</title>
  <dc:creator>Koen Hufkens</dc:creator>
  <link>https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/featured.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Jonas Allert on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was unsure if I would take up personal blogging again. But, a recent <a href="https://mastodon.social/@ct_bergstrom@fediscience.org/111197897996606862">Mastodon post by Carl T. Bergstrom</a> made me realize the value of continuing after refactoring the website.</p>
<p>We are quickly going down the road of total enshitification of the web, due to the convincing nature of Large Language Model (LLM) output (think ChatGPT, Bard etc). The web will soon be filled with reams of auto-generated text not worth reading. To give you some context on where we are headed. Ever look up a recipe online these days? Notice how you had to scroll past pages of text on the life story of the author and why this recipe matters to them, while all you wanted was an ingredients list, food prep instructions and maybe a picture of how pasta puttanesca should look? This will be the web going forward, but EVERYWHERE. Finding trusted sources of information and worthwhile content to read will therefore come at a premium.</p>
<p>I will therefore counter the enshitification of the web, by a handful of platforms, using the approach that made them big, i.e.&nbsp;by linking out.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“It was perhaps the best encapsulation of a mantra I first heard from web pioneer Dave Winer: The more you send people away, the more they come back.” - Philip Bump (<a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/10/05/musk-twitter-news/">Musk is nearly done destroying what made Twitter twitter - Washington Post</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As such, I’ll pivot my old blog to a link blog with commentary and suggested reading links. This resonates with some of the comments I got from friends on some of the reading material I forward. This will also allow me to structure some of my thoughts and keep track of this content myself (as finding it again will increasingly be impossible).</p>
<p>This pivot also serves as a warning. Being a trusted source will become more important than ever. The importance of real life references and quality of the material written or linked to rather than “influencer” presence will dominate again (after a decade of cheap viral content and personalities who ride on it). It never really went away, as life is politics and connection, but for a brief moment one could get away with just being famous online.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To those landing here looking for old resources on the old blog: most of these have been integrated in packages and or tutorials currently reported on the BlueGreen Labs <a href="https://bluegreenlabs.org">website</a> or <a href="https://github.com/bluegreen-labs">github</a> page. If you find yourself searching for an old post, following a dead link, please consider looking there for answers.</p>
</blockquote>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{hufkens2023,
  author = {Hufkens, Koen},
  title = {Fresh Start},
  date = {2023-10-02},
  url = {https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-hufkens2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Hufkens, Koen. 2023. <span>“Fresh Start.”</span> October 2, 2023. <a href="https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/">https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://khufkens.com/posts/restarting-blog/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
